<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Keith L. Pardieck</origin>
        <origin>David J. Ziolkowski, Jr.</origin>
        <origin>Michael Lutmerding</origin>
        <origin>Marie-Anne R. Hudson</origin>
        <pubdate>20180425</pubdate>
        <title>North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset 1966 - 2017, version 2017.0</title>
        <geoform>Electronic text files.</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Laurel, MD</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F76972V8</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The 1966-2017 North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) dataset contains avian point count data for more than 700 North American bird taxa (species, races, and unidentified species groupings). These data are collected annually during the breeding season, primarily in June, along thousands of randomly established roadside survey routes in the United States and Canada. Routes are roughly 24.5 miles (39.2 km) long with counting locations placed at approximately half-mile (800-m) intervals, for a total of 50 stops. At each stop, a citizen scientist highly skilled in avian identification conducts a 3-minute point count, recording every bird seen or heard within a quarter-mile (400-m) radius. Surveys begin 30 minutes before local sunrise and take approximately 5 hours to complete. Routes are sampled once per year, with the total number of routes sampled per year growing over time; just over 500 routes were sampled in 1966, while in recent decades approximately 3000 routes have been sampled annually. In addition to avian count data, this dataset also contains survey date, survey start and end times, start and end weather conditions, a unique observer identification number, route identification information, and route location information including country, state, and BCR, as well as geographic coordinates of route start point, and an indicator of run data quality.</abstract>
      <purpose>The North American Breeding Bird Survey provides scientifically credible measures of the status and trends of North American bird populations, at continental and regional scales, to inform biologically sound conservation and management actions. Key features of the BBS that distinguish it from most other avian monitoring programs are its scientifically rigorous yet straight-forward sampling protocol, the breadth of its geographical coverage, and its temporal longevity. It is unique in providing annual information on population abundance and trends across most of the breeding ranges for hundreds of species simultaneously. Because population change may differ among regions, no other survey is as useful as the BBS for documenting the population status of relatively common and widespread species at a near continental scale. The primary functions of the BBS data are to measure avian population change to help identify species priorities for conservation, and to provide annual avian count data for model-based conservation planning. Yet these data have many potential uses, and researchers continue to find new applications of these data each year to address emerging research and management objectives. Today the BBS data set provides the foundation for non-game landbird conservation in North America. Each year long-term population trends are calculated for more than 400 species recorded on BBS routes. These trends inform researchers and wildlife managers of significant changes in bird population levels and are utilized, along with other indicators, by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Canadian Wildlife Service, state wildlife agencies, and Partners in Flight to establish national and regional avian conservation priorities.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1966</begdate>
          <enddate>2017</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-176.635</westbc>
        <eastbc>-52.678</eastbc>
        <northbc>81.825</northbc>
        <southbc>24.597</southbc>
      </bounding>
      <descgeog>All U.S. states except Hawaii, as well as, all Canadian provinces and territories.  See RegionCodes.txt file for full list of geographic areas (i.e., countries, states, etc.). Geographic coordinates for all route start points can be found in the Routes.csv file.</descgeog>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>birds</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Ecosystems, Status and Trends</themekt>
        <themekey>biodiversity</themekey>
        <themekey>population trends</themekey>
        <themekey>avian point counts</themekey>
        <themekey>relative abundance</themekey>
        <themekey>population distribution</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:5af45ebce4b0da30c1b448ca</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>North America</placekey>
        <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
        <placekey>Canada</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>This database, identified as the North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset, has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the Canadian Wildlife Service of Environment and Climate Change Canada (ECCC). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS and ECCC reserve the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review.  Furthermore, it is released on the condition that the USGS, the U.S. Government, the ECCC, and the Canadian Government may not be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.  Use of these BBS data should be formally recognized in publications, presentations and other outlets via appropriate citation and acknowledgements.  [Citation: Pardieck, K.L., D.J. Ziolkowski Jr., M. Lutmerding and M.-A.R. Hudson. 2018. North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset 1966 - 2017, version 2017.0. U.S. Geological Survey, Patuxent Wildlife Research Center.  https://doi.org/10.5066/F76972V8.]  Additionally, all work using these data should acknowledge the thousands of dedicated U.S. and Canadian participants who annually perform and coordinate the survey.  If a publication is to be based on the analysis of BBS data, we encourage you to read and understand these metadata and supporting documents. The National BBS staff are also available to address any questions regarding the collection and presentation of these data.  Also depending on time constraints and other factors BBS staff may be available to assist with the writing and/or review of the manuscript.  It is in the best interest of the BBS program to demonstrate the utility of the data.  One way we do this is by posting a BBS-based bibliography.  Upon publication of your research, we encourage you to send the National BBS office a quick note with a link to your paper or a pdf copy so we can include it.   Thank you for supporting the BBS program and we look forward to learning of your work.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Keith L. Pardieck</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
          <city>Laurel</city>
          <state>MD</state>
          <postal>20708-4038</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>301-497-5843</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kpardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey Patuxent Wildlife Research Center; Environment Canada, Canadian Wildlife Service</datacred>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>USGS Biocomplexity Thesaurus</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Birds</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxonsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>American Ornithologists' Union</origin>
              <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
              <title>Check-list of North American Birds, 7th ed. (and all subsequent supplements through the 58th supplement)</title>
              <geoform>ONLINE_REFERENCE</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
                <publish>American Ornithologists' Union</publish>
              </pubinfo>
              <onlink>http://www.americanornithology.org/content/checklist-north-and-middle-american-birds</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>R.T. Chesser, K.J. Burns, C. Cicero, J.L. Dunn, A.W. Kratter, I.J. Lovette, P.C. Rasmussen, J. V. Remsen, Jr., J.D. Rising, D.F. Stotz, and K. Winker</origin>
              <pubdate>2017</pubdate>
              <title>Fifty-eighth supplement to the American Ornithological Society’s Check-list of North American Birds</title>
              <geoform>ONLINE_REFERENCE</geoform>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>Unknown</pubplace>
                <publish>The Auk: Ornithological Advances 134:751-773</publish>
              </pubinfo>
              <onlink>https://doi.org/10.1642/AUK-17-72.1</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <ider>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Dave Ziolkowski, Jr.</cntper>
              <cntorg>USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
              <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
              <city>Laurel</city>
              <state>MD</state>
              <postal>20708-4038</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>301-497-5753</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>dziolkowski@usgs.gov</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </ider>
        <taxonpro>expert advice; identification keys</taxonpro>
        <taxoncom>Data are collected by individuals who are highly skilled in aural and visual identification of wild birds.  The data are then reviewed by area experts for accuracy, with appropriate corrections made, as necessary, in consultation with observer, reference works and local area experts.</taxoncom>
      </taxonsys>
      <taxongen>The majority of birds are identified to the level of species. In some cases individuals are identified to race or an unidentified species group. See the file SpeciesList.txt for the list of species and taxa groups. Numerous changes in the taxonomy of North American birds have occurred since 1966, and are described in the sixth and seventh editions of the American Ornithologists' Union Check-list of North American Birds and subsequent supplements. The BBS attempts to maintain a database that reflects these taxonomic and nomenclatural changes. However, in some cases BBS data management needs dictate deviation from the AOU (now the AOS) check-list. For example, when two or more species have been lumped into a single species the BBS usually maintains the former species as separate taxonomic entities within the database. Thus lumping and re-splitting of some species during the history of the BBS has not affected how the data have been treated. When a species is split into two or more species the treatment of existing data within the database is dependent on the population distributions of the new species. If their population distributions are completely disjunct, then assignment of existing data within the database to the new species poses no problems. If the new species' population distributions overlap, then it may not be possible to assign existing data to the appropriate species group, and it may dictate the formation of an indeterminate taxa group composed of the two or more overlapping species. The BBS uses a 5-digit species identification code to uniquely identify taxa within the database. These codes were originally derived from American Ornithologists' Union's species identification numbers, and are referred to as "AOU" numbers in the data tables. [Note: the American Ornithologists' Union is now known as the American Ornithological Society.] The AOU abandoned this numbering system, but it was continued in the numbering system of Sibley and Monroe (1990) [Sibley, C.G., and B.L. Monroe, Jr. 1990. Distribution and taxonomy of birds of the world. Yale University Press, New Haven, CT. 1111p.] The BBS no longer attempts to maintain concordance with either species numbering system. Thus, the "AOU" numbers are simply 5-digit species identification codes used to manage data within the BBS database.</taxongen>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Bilateria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Deuterostomia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Infraphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Gnathostomata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                    <taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
                    <taxonrv>Tetrapoda</taxonrv>
                    <taxoncl>
                      <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                      <taxonrv>Aves</taxonrv>
                      <common>Birds</common>
                      <common>oiseaux</common>
                    </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The data set has been subjected to multiple computerized quality assurance and quality control routines that evaluate the data for computational, value range, and species range errors. Flags raised during the QAQC process are manually reviewed by professional staff for accuracy, with appropriate corrections made in consultation with the observers, reference works, and local area experts. Upon completion of data processing, the observers are asked to complete one final data review to ensure accuracy.</logic>
    <complete>The BBS is an ongoing annual survey. This data set is considered complete at the time of release. Late data returns not included in this release will be included in subsequent releases. BBS Data are housed in MS-SQL 2014 database. Numerous scripts and SQL queries, developed by USGS staff (BBSRetrievalData_V1.5), are used to repackage data into the flat files for the data set release. Users are advised to read the entire metadata record for further details. 
1) BBS data provide an index of population abundance, not a complete count of birds at a stop or on a route.  Only those birds visible or audible to the observer during the 3-minute point count period are identified to species, or appropriate BBS taxa group, and enumerated.   
Weather, habitat, bird activity levels, time of day, ambient noise, human abilities, and much more may affect detection rates of birds.  The BBS controls for many of these factors by utilizing a rigorous and standardized sampling protocol.  Nevertheless, incorporation of covariates  
like observer effects have been shown to play an important role in mitigating bias when analyzing BBS data.  Other important factors include first-time observer effect and sample density.  
Faanes, C. A. and D. Bystrak. 1981. The role of observer bias in the North American Breeding Bird Survey. Pages 353-359 in C. John Ralph and J. Michael Scott Estimating Numbers of Terrestrial Birds.  Studies in Avian Biology 6., 630 pp. http://sora.unm.edu/node/49  
Kendall, W. L., B. G. Peterjohn, and J. R. Sauer. 1996. First-time observer effects in the North American Breeding Bird Survey. Auk 113(4):823-829. http://sora.unm.edu/node/25734  
Link, W. A. and J. R. Sauer. 1997. Estimation of population trajectories from count data. Biometrics 53(2):488-497. http://www.jstor.org/stable/info/2533952  
Sauer, J. R., W. A. Link, and J. A. Royle. 2004. Estimating population trends with a linear model: technical comments. Condor 106(2):435-440. http://www.bioone.org/perlserv/?request=get-abstract&amp;doi=10.1650/7431  
Sauer, J. R. and W. A. Link. 2011. Analysis of the North American Breeding Bird Survey using hierarchical models. Auk 128(1):87-98. http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/auk.2010.09220  

2) Breeding bird species.  Breeding birds are defined as any bird, except dependent young, detected within that species' known local breeding population range and within the accepted breeding season for the region where detected.   
No attempt is made to distinguish between paired and unpaired individuals.  Migrant (a.k.a., migrant, vagrant or nonbreeding) species information has not been consistently collected or stored for most of the survey's history due to survey's focus on breeding species.   
Steps were taken in 1999 to preserve "Migrant" information prospectively; "Migrant" data can be more accurately identified as "NOT-breeder" since the migrant data set contains all data not fitting into the "Breeding" category regardless of data quality.  

3) Sample density (i.e., route density) varies across time and space.  The survey was initiated in different years in different parts of its range.  The BBS began in 1966 with about 500 routes sampled in the United States east of the Mississippi River and in Quebec and the maritime provinces of Canada.  In 1967, the BBS expanded to the central United States, with a few routes in Ontario and Manitoba.  By 1968 approximately 1200 routes were established and being sampled across the contiguous United States and southern half of all Canadian provinces, with only 2-3 routes being sampled in Alaska until the 1980s.  Today there are around 5000 active routes of which approximately 3000 have been sampled annually since the mid-1990s.  However, the same ~3000 routes are not necessarily sampled each year due to variety of reasons, including: poor weather conditions, safety concerns, and participant availability (e.g., illness).  
Many patterns occur in geographic coverage of the BBS.  Some patterns occur as a consequence of logistics.  BBS routes near human population centers tend to be consistently surveyed but remote routes are not surveyed every year, which causes regional variation in the efficiency of the survey (Robbins et al. 1986).  Although all States and Provinces vary in coverage over time, some consistent regional patterns occur in BBS coverage.  Route density varies geographically with regions in the northeast and southeast generally having higher route densities than most western and midwestern regions.  For example, Maryland has approximately 14 routes per degree block, Alabama and Georgia have about 6 routes per degree block, and Nevada and Utah have about 2 routes per degree block.  In Canada, routes are largely restricted to the southern half of the country; a pattern further reflected within individual provinces and territories.  
Lawler, J. J., and R. J. O'Connor. 2004. How well do consistently monitored Breeding Bird Survey routes represent the environments of the conterminous United States? Condor 106:801-814.  
Robbins, C.S., D.A. Bystrak, and P.H. Geissler.  1986.  The Breeding Bird Survey:  its first fifteen years, 1965-1979.  USDOI, Fish and Wildlife Service resource publication 157.  Washington, D.C.  

4) While sample locations (i.e., routes) are established using a stratified random process, they are constrained to roadsides except for a handful of water routes in Alaska and Alabama.  This restricted sampling frame has raised questions regarding the influence of roadside bias.  There are three primary concerns:  
A) habitats along roads may not be representative of habitats in the landscape due to, for example, increased disturbance along roads or placement of roads;  
B) counts may not be representative for some species due to differential attraction to, or avoidance of, roadside habitats;  
C) counts along roads thru time may not be representative due to differing rates of habitat change on roads versus off roads.  
Habitat representation has been fairly well examined in the literature (Bart et al. 1995; Keller and Scallan 1999; Neimuth et al. 2007) with the most comprehensive studies to date Veech et al. (2012, 2017) finding that for most of the 15 NLCD land cover types examined, the habitats within 400m of BBS routes are similar to habitats within 10,000m. Notable exceptions included slight under represenation of open water habitat and a slight over representation of developed open space near routes.  Nevertheless, differences in local habitat quality or roadside attraction/avoidance effects may influence species abundance on roadside counts (Wellicome et al. 2014).  
Bart, J., M. Hofschen, and B. G. Peterjohn. 1995. Reliability of the Breeding Bird Survey: Effects of restricting surveys to roads. Auk 112:758-761.  
Keller, C. M. E., and J. T. Scallan. 1999. Potential roadside biases due to habitat changes along breeding bird survey routes. Condor 101:50-57.  
Niemuth, N. D., A. L. Dahl, M. E. Estey, and C. R. Loesch. 2007. Representation of landcover along Breeding Bird Survey routes in the Northern Plains. Journal of Wildlife Management 71:2258-2265.  
Veech, J. A., M. F. Small, and J. T. Baccus. 2012. Representativeness of Land Cover Composition along Routes of the North American Breeding Bird Survey. Auk 129(2):259-267. (http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1525/auk.2012.11242) (http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/auk.2012.11242)  
Wellicome, T. I., K. J. Kardynal, R. J. Franken, and C. S. Gillies. 2014. Off-road sampling reveals a different grassland bird community than roadside sampling: implications for survey design and estimates to guide conservation. Avian Conservation and Ecology 9(1): 4. http://dx.doi.org/10.5751/ACE-00624-090104  
Veech, J. A., K. L. Pardieck, and D. J. Ziolkowski, Jr. 2017. How well do route survey areas represent landscapes at larger spatial extents? An analysis of land cover composition along Breeding Bird Survey routes. Condor 119: 607-615. https://doi.org/10.1650/CONDOR-17-15.1 

5) The BBS provides a “RunType” code to help a data user to quickly determine which data do, or do not meet the BBS program’s data criteria.  A RunType code of 1 is assigned whenever data were collected under conditions that meet BBS weather, date, time, and route completion criteria (QualityCurrentID = 1) on  
a randomly established route (i.e., RouteTypeDetailID = 1) using the official BBS sampling protocol (RPID = 101).  Conversely, a RunType code of 0 indicates that data from a run fail to meet one or more of the aforementioned requirements.  This could occur in one of 3 scenarios, or in combination,  
when: data exceed suitable date, time, weather, and/or route completion criteria (QualityCurrentID = 0), data had been collected along a non-randomly established route (i.e., RouteTypeDetailID is not 1), and/or when the official BBS sampling protocol had not been used (RPID [RunProtocolID] is not 101).  See RunType.txt file for more information.   
***Please Note: With the 2017 data release, the BBS has modified the way it assigns RunType codes.  In years prior, RPID was not used explicitly in the determination of the RunType code.  It was incumbent upon the user to identify and remove samples that did not meet their desired sample protocol requirements.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data are submitted to the National BBS office by participants via a web-based data entry program. The observer then mails hard copies of completed data forms to BBS office for quality assurance and archiving purposes. The data are subjected to a battery of computerized quality assurance and quality control routines to identify potentially incorrect, out of range, or incomplete data. These data flags are manually reviewed by BBS staff who use expert knowledge, published references, original data sheets, local experts, and communication with observers and regional coordinators to resolve the identified data flags. Once the data flags are resolved, the data are released to the observers for another review. The data are then subjected to a final internal review and data quality is assessed for each run of a route. The BBS provides a “RunType” code to help data users quickly determine which data do or do not meet the BBS program’s data quality criteria. Since 1966 approximately 10% of the route runs submitted have not met the criteria required for inclusion in statistical population analyses. See the file RunType.pdf for further information.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20180301</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Sample locations are established using a stratified random process within a state/province/territory, where the stratification units are 1-degree blocks of latitude-longitude. Site selection is constrained by availability of suitable roads to conduct counts. Sample routes consist of 50 roadside sample locations spaced at approximately 800-meter intervals, as road and safety conditions allow. A 3-minute point count is conducted at each stop by one person, highly skilled in avian identification, who identifies and records all birds detected. Each route starts 30 minutes before local sunrise and takes approximately 5 hours to complete.</methdesc>
        <methcite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>USGS and CWS</origin>
            <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
            <title>Instructions for Conducting the North American Breeding Bird Survey</title>
            <geoform>Document</geoform>
            <onlink>www.pwrc.usgs.gov/bbs/participate/instructions.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </methcite>
      </method>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Data fields and definitions are described in the file NABBS_DataFieldDefinitions_1996-2017.pdf.  Additional information is available in ReadMe.txt and the following lookup files (keys): RegionCodes.txt, BBSStrata.txt, BCR.txt, weathercodes.txt, RunProtocolID.txt, RunType.pdf, SpeciesList.txt.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://doi.org/10.5066/F76972V8</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>GS ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>This database, identified as the North American Breeding Bird Survey Dataset, has been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and the Canadian Wildlife Service of Environment and Climate Change Canada (ECCC). Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS and ECCC reserve the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review.  Furthermore, it is released on the condition that the USGS, the U.S. Government, the ECCC, and the Canadian Government may not be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20200827</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Keith Pardieck</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Patuxent Wildlife Research Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Wildlife Biologist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>12100 Beech Forest Road</address>
          <city>Laurel</city>
          <state>MD</state>
          <postal>20708-4038</postal>
          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>301-497-5843</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kpardieck@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
